Guide to the Enoch A. Bryan Papers 1843-1989
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Enoch A. Bryan Papers
1843-1989
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 579a
Bryan, Enoch Albert, 1855-1941.
8.5 Linear feet of shelf space 17 Boxes
The personal papers of Enoch A. Bryan consist of drafts of speeches, essays, and books, as well as personal, teaching, and business documents.
Enoch A. Bryan was born in Bloomington, Indiana, on May 10, 1855. He received an A.B. degree from Indiana University in 1878 and an A.M. Degree from that university in 1885. He also received an A.M. degree from Harvard University in 1893. He later received Honorary Doctor of Law degrees from Indiana University (1920), Michigan State University (1907), and Washington State University (1929). Bryan was President of Vincennes University from 1882-1893, after serving as the Superintendent of Public Schools in Grayville, Illinois. He came to the State College of Washington (initially called the Agricultural College, Experiment Station, and School of Science of the State of Washington, and now known as Washington State University) in 1893 and served as its president until 1916, when he became the Commissioner of Education for the State of Idaho, from 1917 to 1923. He had failed in 1916 to attain the nomination for a seat in the United States Senate.
Dr. Bryan returned to the State College of Washington in 1923 and was a professor of economic history until 1939, when he became a professor emeritus. During his lifetime he wrote three books: "The Mark in Europe and America", "The History of the State College of Washington", and "Orient Meets Occident or The Advent of the Railways into the Pacific Northwest". Dr. Bryan died in Pullman, Washington, on November 6, 1941.
The personal papers of Enoch A. Bryan include: manuscripts of his books (Series 1); teaching materials, chiefly related to economics (Series 2); personal materials received from the WSU Office of the President (Series 3), including speeches, essays, and personal correspondence and papers; and materials received from the Bryan family (Series 4), including speeches and essays, personal records and papers, and papers related to the Riviera Land Company of Columbia County, Washington.
The papers are arranged to reflect the provenance of the papers, as well as to facilitate access. Accordingly, materials acquired circa 1990 are arranged in sequences separate from the papers acquired circa 1958. The exceptions are the drafts and manuscripts of Bryan's two books, and some of his classroom teaching materials, where related materials have been drawn together irrespective of which lot they originated with. The reason the papers were originally divided is not clear. To some degree the papers transferred in 1950s from the President's office do reflect a more official capacity, for example, many of the speeches are related to matters involving the State College. Likewise the more personal materials transferred circa 1990 tend to include more speeches and essays on literary and philosophic subjects. However, the division is not exclusive and copies or variants of the same text can be found in both lots. The order and arrangement of the speeches and essays follows that which was received by the Libraries. Texts on roughly related topics are grouped, but otherwise it is quite informal, and is neither alphabetical nor chronological. Indeed, many texts have no titles to use in alphabetization and are not dated well enough to allow arrangement in order of date.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Records from the Enoch A. Bryan administration were received from the Washington State University Office of the President circa 1958 (WSU 158). The personal papers were separated from those records, and additional Office of the President and Bryan family accessions (UA 86-26, MS 90-48, MS 90-49), into this collection in 1991.
In 1986-1990, additional Bryan family accessions were received which lead to the the Enoch A. Bryan Family Correspondence, 1840-1961 (Cage 579b), the President Enoch A. Bryan Photographs and Glass Negatives, 1860-1985 (PC 84), and these personal papers being separated from the State College of Washington Office of the President: Enoch A. Bryan Records, 1888-1952 (Archives 158).
Bryan Family Papers, 1930-1989 (Cage 927)
State College of Washington Office of the President: Letters from Prominent Correspondents (Autograph Collection), 1897-1951 (Cage 1616)
Philips Family Papers, circa 1915-1967 (Cage 4559)
Enoch A. Bryan letter to Ben Torpen, Portland, Oregon, 24 May 1915 (Cage 4911)
Enoch A. Bryan Letter To Clifford Armstrong, 1930 October 1 (Cage 4940)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bryan, Enoch Albert, 1855-1941 -- Archives
Bryan family
State College of Washington -- Presidents -- Archives; Agricultural College, Experiment Station, and School of Science of the State of Washington -- Presidents -- Archives; Vincennes University -- Presidents -- Archives; Riviera Land Company (Columbia Co., Wash.)
College presidents -- Washington (State) -- Pullman.
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities
- Series 1: Manuscripts of books by E. A. Bryan
  - Manuscript, "A Historical Sketch of the State College of Washington", 1890-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Manuscript, "A Historical Sketch of the State College of Washington," 1890-1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript, "Orient Meets Occident," undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Orient Meets Occident: Advent of the Railways to the Pacific Northwest," undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Orient Meets Occident," Correspondence, 1939, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Orient Meets Occident," Original Photographs and Maps used, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Railroad Maps, etc. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Edited Review of "Orient Meets Occident" (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Drafts, "Orient Meets Occident" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Drafts, "Orient Meets Occident" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Drafts, "Orient Meets Occident" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Galley Proof, "Orient Meets Occident" (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Teaching materials, chiefly on economics
  - Economics, undated (Box 4, Folder 17-28)
  - Economics 100: Economic History (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Economics 101: Fishery in Pacific Northwest Railway (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Economics 101: Fruits (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Economics 101: Minerals and Livestock (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Economics 101: Seattle (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Economics 110: Economic History (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Economics: Oceanic Gateways (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Grant of privilege from Russia to Construct an International Telegraph (document) (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Oregon (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Alaska (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Alaska On Travel and Adventure in the Territory of Alaska by Frederick Whymper (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Series 3. Materials acquired from President's Office, circa 1958
  - Series 3.1: Speeches, essays, etc.
    - Agricultural Education
      - A National System of Education (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Teaching Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Higher Agricultural Education (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - to: Editor Rural Spirit (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Methods of Agricultural Instruction (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - What Does Agricultural Education Include (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Agricultural Education- Does it Pay? (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 41-42)
      - To the Board of Regents, WAC and SofS (Report 1895) (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Fragment re: agricultural education (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Does Ocean Shipping (illegible)? (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Suggestions of topics for papers and discussions (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - to: Carl Gray, Hill Lines, RR (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Address of President Bryan at the Fourth Annual Session of the Winter School for Farmers (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: profitability of farming; First Wheat Convention (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: advocacy of mules (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Fragment (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Extension service, circa 1928 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, address to dairy association; Untitled, re: conversion of the West to agriculture (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Special (press release) to Post Intelligencer re: Corn growing contest (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Address of Elwood Mead at Tacoma, April 1904 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Wheat Growers, Shippers and Millers mtg. (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Fragment, re: agricultural journalism (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Wheat Smut (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Smut (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Banker-Farmer Convention (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Agricultural potential of Washington (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Holden Speech, Spokane Club, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Soil analysis (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Cheese making (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Mr. Insinger, re: Dry Farming experimentation (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: Agricultural problem in Big Bend Country (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Untitled, re: State agricultural policy (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Adaptation of the Live Stock Industry to the State of Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Poultry in Washington Agriculture; Dry Land Alfalfa; Dairy History (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Relation of Research to Demonstration Work in Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Changes in the Department of Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The College Herd (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Untitled, re: Swine industry (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Small Orchard (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Why has Soil Erosion in the Palouse Country Increased? (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - From the Range to the Ranch; Transportation of Poultry Products and Feeds (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - American Agriculture and European Markets (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Fall and Rise of the Dairy Industry in Western Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Western Washington Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Agricultural Lands in Western Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Poultry in Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - That Agricultural Bloc, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Outline Suggestions for A Policy for Washington Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Dr. Bryan's Toll Gate Story (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Grasses and Cereals in Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Agricultural Revolution (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Livestock Situation in Washington (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Little Orchard Again (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Tweedle-dum and Tweedle-dee (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Factors Affecting World Consumption of Wheat (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Political Solidarity of Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - How the Open Range Disappeared (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Moses and Aaron (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Margin of Profit to the Farmer (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Speculation (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Agriculture Holds its Place (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Agriculture in the Schools (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Principles of Live stock Judging (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Cheap Feed and High Priced Hogs (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Farmers Meeting at Bellingham, July 16, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Livestock History (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Teaching Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Aged Ewe (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Factors Affecting World Consumption of Wheat (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - For the Farm Trio, Industry-Commerce-Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Production of Beef Cattle on a 160 Acre Farm (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - How to Provide Cavalry Horses (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The New Agriculture (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - The Country Life Commission (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Duplication of Courses at University and State College
      - There is Plenty of Room for Both (by Geo. Newman) (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Dear Mr. Perkins, re: duplication controversy (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Dear Mr. Paulhamus, re: mission of college (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Correspondence with Suzzallo and others (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Untitled, re: Duplication issue (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - The Scientific School Lands Belonging to the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Untitled statement of the point of view of the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - To the Editor (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Fragment, on envelope (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Confidential, re: mission of college (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Untitled, re: duplication (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Untitled, re:, excess praise for the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Statement by J. L. Ashlock (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Press release, Pullman Chamber of Commerce (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Untitled (Same as Confidential, above) (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Two Universities (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - What is the great issue between the University and the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Fragment, re: duplication (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Some things the State College will lose of the Recommendations of the Experts are adopted (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - The Cost of Duplication (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Memoranda (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - General Statement of the Position of the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Fact Concerning the Phony Brief of Dean Condon of University of Washington Law School (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Chapter VI: Present Scope and Functions of the"State College and the State University (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Chapter VII. Duplication and the Principle of Major Lines (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Chapter VIII. Differentiation of Washington State Higher Institutions (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Chapter IX. Education in the State College and University (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Chapter X. Minor Questions of Administration and Recommendations (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - The Legal Status of the Functions of the State College of Washington and the University of Washington (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - The Agricultural College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Matching Dollars (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - University and State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - An Act relating to the University of Washington and the State College of Washington (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Committee of Experts commend the Work of the State College (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - History of Duplication, by Robert Cowan, President of Yakima Club. (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Economics (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Little Lesson on Economic Subjects: (by Jacob Sonnenschein, possibly a pen name) (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - How Did Property Originate? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - Who Fixes the Price? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - Who Pays the Taxes? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - Who Pays the Freight? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - How Shall We Build Our Roads? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - Who is the Producer? (Box 6, Folder 44)
        - How Shall We Build Our Roads? (Duplicate from above) (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - The Economic Interpretation of History (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Economic Outlook for Washington (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Overheard (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Advantages of Organization and Co-operation (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Ocean Steamers (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - The Economic Program of American Women (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Some Early and Unwritten History of Electric Development in Spokane (by J.B. Fisken) (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - History (The Washington Water Power Company) (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - A Typical Hydro-Electric Development in the Pacific Northwest (Idaho Power Co.) (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Navigation of the Columbia and Snake (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Water Power Development in the Pacific Northwest (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Review of Legislation and Decisions Affecting Irrigation and Water Rights therefor in the State of Washington (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Untitled, re: electricity in Oregon (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Notes, chiefly re: history of Washington Water Power Co. (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Econ. 101, paper re: electricity (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Puget Sound Power and Light (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Hydro-Electric Development of the P.N.W. (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Notes (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Water Resources of the P.N.W. (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Radio Service (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Fragments, notes, etc. re: water, electricity, etc. (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Education
      - Education in the Inland Empire (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Colleges for More than Sport (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Educational Needs of Country Life (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Opening the Eyes of the Blind (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Vocational Education in Secondary Education (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - National Aid for Industrial Education (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Agricultural Schools (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Some Problems of Primary Education School Officers (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - The Relation of the Teacher and the Citizen to SocialProblems (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Education
      - Untitled, re: public education rationale (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Extract from Address to Spokane High School, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Notes, from David Starr Jordan on education (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Untitled, re: "common schools" (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Extract from Address of Commissioner E.A. Bryan at the N.E.A. Salt Lake (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Untitled, begins--Ladies and Gentlemen (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Relation of Liberal Education to the Community (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Aristocratic vs. the Democratic Theory of Education Research (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - State, County, and Local Responsibility for Education (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Modern University (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Country Life Commission (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Shall the Instruction and Curriculum of the Public High School be prescribed by the Colleges and Universities (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - What is the Matter with the Public Schools (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Rationalizing Education (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Recent Status of Scientific Education and How it Came to Pass (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Post-War Education (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Democratic Theory of Education (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Democratic vs Aristocratic View of Education, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Should there be a Language Requirement for Graduation (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Industrial Democracy (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Does the Pursuit of a College Course Lessen a Young Man's Chances for Success in Business (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Tentative Proposals of the Resolutions Committee of WEA (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - New Duties (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - American Colleges and Universities (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Progress of Educational Thought (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Relation of the Teacher to the State (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Commercial Teacher (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Professor Beach's View of Military Training in Universities (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - The Part of the State in Education (Cheney, 1932) (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - Code of Public Instruction (Box 7, Folder 47)
      - A National System of Education (3 copies) (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Educational Survey Commission, 1915-17 (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Why the Educational Survey Report Should be Rejected (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Reasons for State College (1905) (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Why the State College Does Not Accept the Report of the Educational Survey Experts (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Untitled, re: Educational Survey (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Reporter in Davenport Hotel (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - To the editor of the Post Intelligencer (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Instances of Inaccuracies, Clerical and otherwise in the Experts' Report (Box 7, Folder 48)
      - Stenographic report of the remarks of President Bryan before the Joint Committee ... 1915 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Fashions and Fads
      - Untitled, re: Fashions (Box 7, Folder 49)
      - Fads and Frills (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Farmers and Farming
      - A National Agrarian Party (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Decentralization of Population (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - To the Editor of the Pacific Farmer (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - The Price of Farm Products (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - What Shall He so with the Money? (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - What Shall the Farmer do for his Children, signed Jacob Sonnenschien (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Farmers Institutes (2 copies) (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - The Farm Census of 1910 (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Why not Quit? (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - If the Farmer Should Strike (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - For Better or for Worse (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - The Family Row (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Washington for the Immigrant (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Is Diversified Farming a Failure (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - A Southern Idaho Farmers Story (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Extension Work and Farmer Institutes (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Analysis of Farm Income (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - The Farmer and Forestry (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Farm Bookkeeping (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Checking the Cityward Drift (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Why the Boy Leaves the Farm (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - America's Country Home (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Be Reasonable (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - A Statement of Mr. W.J. Spillman's Service to Agriculture (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Forestry and Logged-off Land (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Utilizing the Logged-off Lands (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Forestry Education in Idaho (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Forest have Proved Basis of Industries (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Dean Francis A. Miller (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Extract from Article Written by Dr. JohnMcLaughlin (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - The Forests and Forest Products of the Pacific Northwest (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Clearing the Logged-off Land and Char-pitting Up-to-date (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - The Forest and Forest Products of the Pacific Northwest (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Federal Aid for Logged-off Land (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Untitled, re: burning stumps and slash (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Untitled, re: burning stumps (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Part of the Address of H.W. Sparks, ... to the Logged-off Land Association, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Lecture Delivered by H.W. Sparks ... Portland, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Stump-burning in Sandy Soil (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - To Editor, Spokesman Review, re: logged-off land (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Higher Education
      - Some Recent Changes in the Theory of Higher Education (2 copies) (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - House Bill 69 Relating to State Institutions of Higher Education (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - The Will to Learn and the Ability (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Chapter 4. General Considerations of Higher Education in Washington (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Chapter 2. The Support of Higher Education in Washington and other States (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - The Recent Status of Scientific Education and How it Came to Pass (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - The Value of Higher Education to the Individual and tothe Community (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - The Relationship of Higher Education to the Community (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Extract from address to Men's Club, Plymouth Congregational Church, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Problem 1. Is Higher Education in this State Costing too Much (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Clog Dancing Again (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - History--U.S. and Pacific Northwest